The parent function is the most basic function.
We can apply transformations to our parent function
which changes its size, shape, or orientation.
The parent function y equals x is known as a Linear
function. Its parent graph has the shape of a straight diagonal
line extending through the origin of the x y plane. The
domain is from negative infinity to positive infinity. The range is
from negative infinity to positive infinity as well.
The parent function y equals x squared is known as the
Quadratic function. Its parent graph has a U shape called a
parabola. The domain is from negative infinity to positive infinity. The
range is from zero included in the set to positive infinity.
The parent function y equals x cubed is known as a
Cubic function. The domain is from negative infinity to positive infinity.
The range is from negative infinity to positive infinity as well.
The parent function y equals the absolute value of x is known
as the Absolute Value function. Its parent graph has a recognizable V
shape. The domain is from negative infinity to positive infinity. The range
is from zero included in the set to positive infinity.
The parent function y equals b raised to the x is
known as the Exponential function. Its parent graph has the shape
of what is called an exponential curve. The domain is from
negative infinity to positive infinity. The range is from zero not
included in the set to positive infinity.
The parent function y equals the square root of x is
known as the Square root function. The domain is from zero
included in the set to positive infinity. The range is from
zero included in the set to positive infinity.