Here we have the parent graph of
our quadratic function y equals x squared.
If we want to translate our graph up,
we simply add to the parent function.
If we add 5 to the parent function, we now have y equals
x squared plus five. This will translate the graph up five units.
Let's restore back to our parent graph
again and remove the five we added.
If we wanted to translate our parent function
down, we subtract from the parent function.
Subtracting three from the parent function will
shift the graph down three units.
Removing our minus three restores our parent graph.
Now if we want to translate our graph to the
right we would subtract from inside the parent function.
Notice we subtracted four from x inside the parentheses of our
parent function. It is x minus 4 squared instead of x
squared minus 4. This will translate the graph right four units
Here we are back to our parent function.
To translate our graph to the left, we add to the parent function.
Adding two to x inside the parent
function shifts the graph left two units.
Let's look at more transformations with another
parent graph, the square root function.
A negative sign on the outside shows a reflection across the x axis
So if we put a negative on the outside of our
square root we see the graph flips across the x axis.
Removing the negative restores our parent graph.
A negative sign on the inside shows a reflection across the y axis.
If we apply a negative directly to x inside the square root, the
graph flips across the y axis and is now pointing to the left.
You can see the importance of where you place a negative
sign to your parent function. A negative on the outside will
flip the graph across the x axis and a negative being
multiplied to x inside flips the graph across the y axis.
Let us return to our quadratic parent graph.
Multiplying by a number bigger than 1 stretches the function
If we multiply x squared by two, we stretch the graph
by a factor of two which makes the graph appear taller.
Here is our parent graph.
Multiplying by a number less than 1
(fraction or decimal) shrinks the function
If we multiply x squared by zero point five, we
are shrinking the graph by a factor of zero point
five which makes the graph appear shorter or wider.