In this example we are asked to describe the transformation.
Here our equation is y equals negative absolute value of x plus
four, then outside the absolute value sign we have a minus seven
If you remember, transformations are what we apply to our
parent function so let's first take out our parent function
from the equation and apply each transformation step by step.
Since there is an x written inside an absolute value symbol
from our original equation, we know that y equals the absolute
value of x is going to be our parent function.
Next, we see we are adding four to x inside the absolute value symbol.
Since we are adding four inside the parent function
we will shift the graph left four units.
We are also multiplying a negative to
the outside of the absolute value.
A negative on the outside will reflect
the parent graph across the x axis.
Finally, we are subtracting seven at the end of the equation.
Our final transformation then will to shift the graph down seven
units. Now that we have all of our transformations laid out
let's see how this will transform our parent graph.
Here is our parent graph of y equals the absolute value of x.
Adding four to x inside the absolute
value shifts the graph left four units.
Then if we place a negative on the outside of
the absolute value the graph reflects over the x axis.
Lastly, we subtract seven from the whole absolute value term
which shifts our graph down seven units. After applying these
transformations, our new equation has now become y equals the
negative absolute value of x plus four minus seven.
Let's look at another example. Again
we want to describe the transformation.
Here our equation is two times the absolute
value of x minus one plus three.
If you remember again, transformations are what we apply to our
parent function so let's first take out our parent function from
the equation and apply each transformation step by step.
y equals the absolute value of x is our parent function.
Then we subtract one from x inside the absolute value sign.
This will shift the graph right one unit.
Next we multiply two on the outside of the absolute value symbol.
Since two is greater than one, we will
stretch the graph by a factor of two.
Finally we add three to the end of the equation.
Adding three will shift the graph up three
units. Now let's see how the transformations we
have ust described will transform our parent graph.
Here we are back to our parent graph for our
parent function y equals the absolute value of x.
Inside the absolute value we subtract one from x
which shifts the graph to the right one unit.
Then we multiply two to the outside of the absolute
value and stretch the graph by a factor of two.
Last but not least, we add three to the absolute value term and
shift our graph up three units. So after applying our transformation, our new
function is y equals two times the absolute value of x minus one
plus three and our graphs shape and position has changed.
In our next example, we are told to translate an absolute
value function four units to the left, and seven units down.
Since we are translating an absolute value function, we know our
parent function will be y equals the absolute value of x.
This is our parent function.
Next we will add four to x inside the absolute value symbol.
This translates or shifts the function to the left four units.
Lastly, we will subtract seven.
This will translate function down seven units. Having applied
our translations let's see how this would look graphically.
Here we have an absolute value function's parent graph.
To translate left four units, we add four
to x inside the absolute value function.
Then to translate down seven units, we simply subtract seven outside the
absolute value term. So after applying our translations, our new function becomes
y equals the absolute value of x plus four minus seven.
In our next example we are asked to translate a quadratic function three
units to the right and stretch it by a factor of two.
Since we are asked to translate a quadratic
function, we can write y equals x squared.
This quadratic function is our parent function.
Next, we want to translate our quadratic function three units
to the right. To do this we will subtract three
from inside our parent function so the equation now becomes
y equals then in parentheses, x minus three squared.
Subtracting three inside the parentheses will
translate the function right three units.
Next we multiply by two outside the parentheses.
This will stretch it by a factor of two. Now with all of
our translations taken care of let's see how this would look graphically.
Here is the parent graph of our quadratic function y equals x squared.
Subtracting three from x inside the function
will shift the graph right three units.
Then multiplying by two will stretch the graph by a factor of two.